<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Cody Hatch - Notes on data science and cyber security - Tools</title><link href="https://codyhatch.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://codyhatch.com/feeds/tools.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://codyhatch.com/</id><updated>2016-09-11T16:35:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>General Conference Word Frequency Estimator</title><link href="https://codyhatch.com/tools/genconf-word-frequency.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-11T16:35:00-06:00</published><updated>2016-09-11T16:35:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Cody Hatch</name></author><id>tag:codyhatch.com,2016-09-11:/tools/genconf-word-frequency.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;LDS General Conference word frequency estimator&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently updated a simple word frequency estimator for LDS General Conference talks that I have on GitHub. I had originally hacked it together but figured I'd update it to use the Python Natural Language Toolkit (NLTK) and a count vectorizor for word counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the code at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/orangganjil/gen-conf-word-frequency"&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tools"></category><category term="Analysis"></category></entry><entry><title>DNS Registrar Checker</title><link href="https://codyhatch.com/tools/dns-registrar-checker.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-14T19:35:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-08-14T19:35:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Cody Hatch</name></author><id>tag:codyhatch.com,2015-08-14:/tools/dns-registrar-checker.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Script to check your domain registrar to see if your DNS has been hijacked.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote a basic, hacked together Perl script to check domain registrar information and determine whether the DNS for your domain has been hijacked. I wrote the script a while ago in Perl and, since it works fine, I haven't bothered to change it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few key things to note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You'll need to adjust some of the variables to fit your environment (e.g., domains, allowed IPs for DNS servers, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recommend that this run on a server or something where you can schedule it via cron to run at regular intervals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recommend that you include administrative emails for notification that are not part of the domains this script monitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If possible, run this from a server that can utilize split DNS to avoid any potential issues if the admin domains are hijacked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is a quickly hacked-together script but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is available at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/orangganjil/dns-registrar-checker"&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tools"></category><category term="Security"></category></entry></feed>